BU Records: Philomathesian Literary Society, Inclusive: 1859-1951, undated, Bulk: 1880-1913
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
BU Records: Philomathesian Literary Society
Inclusive: 1859-1951, undated, Bulk: 1880-1913
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
BU/130
Philomathesian Literary Society
8 document boxes and 4 oversized boxes
The BU Records: Philomathesian Literary Society consist of literary and legal productions, financial documents, and correspondence generated during their period of existence at Baylor University. These records include roll books, minutes books, general business records, library records, their constitution, contest records, and records on their fight with the Erisophian Literary Society from 1912-1913.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Poor.
Biography/Profile
Established in 1851 while Baylor University was located in Independence, Texas, the Philomathesian Literary Society was the first literary society to be established in Texas. The Philomathesians’ motto was “Esse quam videri malo,” which is Latin for “to be, rather than to seem to be,” and their colors were white and blue to represent purity and sincerity. During regular meetings, they held debates, orations, and wrote essays about a variety of controversial and conversational topics not covered in university classes. The society was formed not only to boost oratory skills and intellectual growth but also as a social organization to promote extracurricular activities among the students.
The Philomathesian Literary Society consisted only of male members, as did their rivals, the Erisophian Literary Society, which formed after half of the “Philos” separated in 1867. Baylor also boasted two female literary societies, the Calliopean Literary Society formed in 1867 and the Rufus C. Burleson Society formed in 1888. Society rivalry was rampant between the literary societies, eventually leading to the alliance of the Philomathesians with the “Callies” and the “Sophies” with the “R.C.B.s”. Each society engaged in active recruitment; enlisting new members was fiercely competitive and led to members of the male organizations illegally recruiting incoming freshmen while riding the trains to Waco. Students considered committing membership to a society an essential part of student life. One of the editors of the Baylor Literary, the monthly publication of the Philomathesians and Erisophians, commented that “no man can be a real Baylor man apart from his society EL the most potent power in Baylor’s existence has always been that of her literary societies.”
The four literary societies maintained a large collection of books for use of their respective members. By 1900, the Philomathesian Literary Society owned 1,700 books, mostly standard works and classics. About five percent of the collection was religious. The Erisophians held around 1,900 books and the female societies had 700 books, mostly fiction. In contrast, the University library amounted to 4,000 books, but this was not regarded as the best collection, being made up of such donated books as students could spare. The literary societies decided to donate their library collections to the Baylor library once the new building, Carroll Library, was completed in 1903, making their books available for use by all students.
The presence and prominence of the Philomathesians and the other literary societies at Baylor began to decline by the early 1920s due to an increase interest in athletics and other aspects of student life, such as Greek organizations. As the literary societies began to decline, other student organizations took interest in the societies’ usual activities, such as debate. Baylor’s strong background in debate can be directly attributed to the Philomathesians and the other literary societies, which eventually led to Baylor's modern debate team.
Scope and Content
The BU Records: Philomathesian Literary Society begins in 1859 and ends in 1951, though most of the collection occurs between 1880 and 1913. Most of the collection comprises bound volumes created by the members, especially the officers, of the Philomathesian Literary Society during their existence at Baylor University. The roll books span from 1883-1910, which would be an excellent source for determining membership along with the register book and the numerous membership certificates found throughout many of the bound volumes. The minutes books provide a history of the Society from 1859-1916 that can be added to by the compilation of business records in scrapbook-like bound document volumes. Extensive records on books in the possession and protection of the Philomathesians maintain complete inventories and book circulation from various years, showing the growth of the Philomathesians’ collection until they donated all of their books to the Baylor library in the early 1900s. The periodical records from 1896-1900 document which periodicals and formal magazines the society subscribed. One book titled the Philomathesian Literary Review documents articles written by members for various volumes of the society’s publication from 1869 to 1876. Correspondence records exist in this collection between the Philomathesians and Erisophians that occurred between 1912 and 1913 on a disagreement about how the debates from that year should be structured. These fight records emphasize the tension and rivalry between the two groups.
Arrangement
The BU Records: Philomathesian Literary Society are arranged in 4 series: I. Literary Productions, II. Legal Productions, III. Financial Documents, IV. Correspondence.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. BU/130.
Related Resources
Items in related collections
BU Records: Calliopean Literary Society, Inclusive: 1885-1901, undated, Bulk: 1885-1901, undated
BU Records: Rufus C. Burleson Society, Inclusive: 1900-1919
Related references
Eugene W. Baker. To Light the Ways of Time: An Illustrated History of Baylor University, 1845-1986. Waco: Baylor University Press, 1987.
Bishop, Liz. “BU debate team No. 1 in country.” The Lariat. 2004 October 19. Accessed 2012 November 8.
Rollolazo, Sean Jordan. "Literary Societies: The Spirit of Baylor University." HESA Baylor History Project. Accessed 2012 November 8.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University. Philomathesian Literary Society.
Genres
By-laws.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Membership lists.; Minutes (Records)
- Legal Documents, 1859-1898, 1907-1916, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Poor.
  Biography/Profile
  The Legal Documents series contains mainly minutes books from the Philomathesians regular meetings as well as constitutions from different years. Loose material from some of the minutes books has been taken out and put in a separate consecutive folder. Some minutes books have been separated into oversized boxes. The collection is in poor condition.
  - Minutes Book, 1859-1868 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes Book: Loose Material, 1859-1868 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes Book, 1873-1875 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes Book, 1877-1880 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes Book, 1880-1883 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes Book: Loose Material, 1880-1883 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes Book, 1883-1885 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes Book: Loose Material, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes Book, 1885-1890 (Box 12 OVZ., Folder 1)
  - Minutes Book: Loose Material, 1894, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes Book, 1890-1898 (Box 12 OVZ., Folder 2)
  - Minutes Book: Loose Material, 1896-1897 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Minutes Book, 1907-1916 (Box 9 OVZ., Folder 1)
  - Minutes Book: Loose Material, 1902, 1911, 1914-1915, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Constitution, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Constitution and By-laws, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Constitution and By-laws, 1890, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Literary Productions, 1883-1910, undated; 2
  This series contains mostly roll books that maintain membership records. The register book lists members alphabetically along with the date they joined the Society. The dates for this volume were taken from the loose material. The business records are scrapbook-like volumes in which loose papers and letters referring to general business of the society’s officers, committees, and general members have been attached to the inside binding. Much of the documents from these bound volumes have become loose material that was put in separate consecutive folders. The volume labeled the Philomathesian Literary Review contains articles written by members for the publication and recorded in this book. The contest records document the outcome of certain contests, such as debates and oral speeches, held between members of Philomathesians and the Erisophians and literary societies at other universities. Some of the business records and the register book have been put into oversized boxes. This series is in poor condition.
  - Roll Book, 1883-1891 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Roll Book: Loose Material 1, 1891-1892, 1902-1903, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Roll Book: Loose Material 2, 1902-1903, 1910-1911, 1916, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Roll Book, 1884-1888 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Roll Book, 1890-1893 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Roll Book: Loose Material, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Roll Book, 1894-1900 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Roll Book: Loose Material, 1900, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Roll Book, 1900-1905 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Roll Book, 1907-1910 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Business Records, 1885-1892 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Business Records: Loose Material 1, 1891-1892, 1894, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Business Records: Loose Material 2, 1892, 1894, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Business Records: Loose Material 3, 1891-1892 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Business Records, 1891-1894 (Box 11 OVZ., Folder 1)
  - Business Records: Loose Material 1, 1892-1894, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Business Records: Loose Material 2, 1892-1894, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Business Records, 1895-1898 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Business Records: Loose Material, 1892, 1894-1895, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Business Records, 1897-1900 (Box 11 OVZ., Folder 2)
  - Business Records: Loose Material, 1898, 1900, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Register Book, 1908-1919 (Box 10 OVZ., Folder 1)
  - Register Book: Loose Material 1, 1910-1911, 1913, 1915, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Register Book: Loose Material 2, 1910-1911 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Register Book: Loose Material 3, 1910-1911, 1913, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Register Book: Loose Material 4, 1908, 1910-1912, 1915, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Register Book: Loose Material 5, 1915, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Register Book: Loose Material 6, 1910, 1915, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Register Book: Loose Material 7, 1912, 1915-1916 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Register Book: Loose Material 8, 1910, 1912-1913, 1915-1916, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Philomathesian Literary Review, 1869-1876 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Contest Records, 1897-1905 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Financial Documents, 1880-1903, undated; 3
  This series contains records of all of the books in the Philomathesians’ possession and includes documentation of book circulation. Each folder retained the original titles of the volumes given by the Philomathsians, some of the volumes contain much of the same information. The periodical records book documents the periodicals and other formal magazines that the secretary subscribed to for the organization’s use. This series is in poor condition.
  - Library Record, 1880-1885 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Librarian’s Book Register, 1891 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Librarian’s Book, 1891-1894 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Librarian’s Book: Loose Material 1, 1901-1903, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Librarian’s Book: Loose Material 2, 1892, 1902-1904, 1915, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Librarian’s Book, 1894-1896 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Librarian’s Book: Loose Material, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Library Catalogue, 1893-1899 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Library Catalogue: Loose Material, 1894, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Book Schedule, 1889, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Book Schedule: Loose Material, 1873 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Periodical Records, 1896-1900 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Periodical Records: Loose Material, 1900-1901 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Treasurer’s Book, 1900-1903 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Treasurer’s Book: Loose Material, 1902, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1912-1951, undated; 4
  General condition: Good.
  The correspondence series contains records of a dispute between the Philomathesians and the Erisophians over the arrangement of a debate. The letters in this series show the conversation and repeated attempts to come to a consensus on who is in charge of what during the set-up of a debate. This series is in good condition.
  - Fight, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Fight, 1912-1913, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Fight, 1913, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Fight, 1912-1913, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 10)